export const GOVERNMENTA2006 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. According to the Karl Marx, the correct order in which societies progress is",
A: "communism, socialism, capitalism, feudalism",
B: "Feudalism, capitalism, socialism, communism",
C: "Feudalism, socialism, capitalism, communism",
D: "Capitalism, feudalism, communism, socialism",
answer: "B. Feudalism, capitalism, socialism, communism",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. The mandate to direct and command people is",
A: "Power",
B: "Order",
C: "Authority",
D: "Charisma",
answer: "C. Authority",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. The first fascist party was founded by",
A: "Benito Mussolini",
B: "Joseph Stalin",
C: "Adolf Hitler",
D: "Ho Chi Minh",
answer: "A. Benito Mussolini",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. The concept of rule of law was popularized by",
A: "J.J. Rousseau.",
B: "V. Dicey",
C: "Jeremy Bentham",
D: "Baron de Montesquieu",
answer: "B. V. Dicey",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. The right of a citizen to work to work for a living is a/ an",
A: "social right",
B: "personal right",
C: "legal right",
D: "economic right",
answer: "D. economic right",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. Ceremonial and executive powers are usually fused in a system of government known as",
A: "Unitary",
B: "parliamentary",
C: "presidential",
D: "federal",
answer: "C. presidential",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. In a legislative house, a bill is almost certain to be passed after the",
A: "committee stage",
B: "report stage",
C: "second reading",
D: "third reading",
answer: "D. third reading",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. Statutory instrument is a form of",
A: "Proposed law",
B: "Judicial precedence",
C: "Delegated legislation",
D: "Ministerial responsibility",
answer: "C. Delegated legislation",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. When a minister of state is prosecuted for overspending, it is an example of",
A: "rule of law",
B: "parliamentary sovereignty",
C: "judicial review",
D: "ministerial responsibility",
answer: "D. ministerial responsibility",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. The official report of parliamentary proceedings is called",
A: "Hansard",
B: "Kangaroo",
C: "Propagation",
D: "Filibuster",
answer: "A. Hansard",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. Decentralization as a system of administration is desirable because it allows",
A: "central government to control citizens directly",
B: "Effective participation of local administration",
C: "Local authority to exercise sovereign power",
D: "Local authority to conduct its separate foreign policy",
answer: "B. Effective participation of local administration",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. Which of the following is a condition for representative government?",
A: "Organized mob action against the opposition party",
B: "Thorough gerrymandering",
C: "Appointment of party officials as electoral officers",
D: "Existence of periodic, free and fair elections",
answer: "D. Existence of periodic, free and fair elections",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. A law made by a non-parliamentary body is called",
A: "Centralization",
B: "Decentralization",
C: "delegated legislation",
D: "enactment",
answer: "C. delegated legislation",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. A written document embodying the general rules which regulate the functions of government in a state is called",
A: "a legislation",
B: "a constitution",
C: "a statute",
D: "an executive.",
answer: "B. a constitution",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. Which of the following is a feature of a constitution?",
A: "Right to live under anarchy",
B: "Composition and functions of organs of government",
C: "Revenue appropriation to the central government only",
D: "Procedure for acquiring more territories",
answer: "B. Composition and functions of organs of government",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. The provisions of a constitution may be supplemented by",
A: "statutory instrument",
B: "a decree",
C: "others from the council of state",
D: "customs and conventions",
answer: "D. customs and conventions",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. In which of the following system of government does the principle of collective responsibility exit?",
A: "Monarchical",
B: "presidential",
C: "federal",
D: "parliamentary",
answer: "D. parliamentary",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. In a unitary constitution, governmental powers are",
A: "concentrated as the center",
B: "greater in the region than as the center",
C: "Shared equally between the center and the regions",
D: "shared among the three organs",
answer: "A. concentrated as the center",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. Which of the following function falls within the exclusive list?",
A: "Customs and Excise",
B: "Medical provisions",
C: "University ownerships",
D: "Private school ownerships",
answer: "A. Customs and Excise (Typically a federal/central government responsibility)",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. The power of the Prerogative of Mercy is exercised by the …………",
A: "president",
B: "Council of state",
C: "Speaker",
D: "Ruling party",
answer: "A. president",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. The power to declare any act of both the executive and the legislature null and void is known as",
A: "mandamus",
B: "Judicial review",
C: "habeas corpus",
D: "Referendum",
answer: "B. Judicial review",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. One advantage of unicameralism is that it",
A: "considers the old for political appointments",
B: "Consider decision of the legislature",
C: "enables law to be made more quickly",
D: "Enables the head of state to rule well",
answer: "C. enables law to be made more quickly",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. Which of the following is not an obligation of the citizen?",
A: "Observing traffic regulations",
B: "Assisting law enforcement agencies",
C: "Respect for national symbols",
D: "Confrontation with the government",
answer: "D. Confrontation with the government",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. Citizenship is acquired through all the following except",
A: "Conferment",
B: "Marriage",
C: "Nationalization",
D: "Birth",
answer: "A. Conferment (Citizenship can be granted by the state.)",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. The primary goal of a political party is to . . .",
A: "topple on exiting government",
B: "Explain it manifesto to the electorate",
C: "Oppose the ruling government",
D: "capture political power",
answer: "D. capture political power",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. One disadvantage of a one-party system is that it",
A: "Can lead to dictatorship",
B: "Promote strong opposition",
C: "Encourages political education of the citizenry",
D: "Encourages a peaceful change of government",
answer: "A. Can lead to dictatorship",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. Universal adult suffrage means that",
A: "Elected representatives can vote at elections",
B: "Only the wealthy can vote",
C: "Only members of the executive can vote in parliament",
D: "All eligible adults are allowed to vote",
answer: "D. All eligible adults are allowed to vote",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. The right of people to vote for persons to represent them in the legislature is known as",
A: "constitutionalism",
B: "enfranchisement",
C: "obligation",
D: "disenfranchisement",
answer: "B. enfranchisement",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. Elections serve all the following purposes except",
A: "enabling every qualified adult to participate in politics",
B: "making leaders accountable to the people",
C: "enabling political parties to form a government",
D: "making it difficult to remove leaders",
answer: "D. making it difficult to remove leaders (Elections should make leaders accountable, not more difficult to remove.)",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. An Independent candidate in an election is the one",
A: "who belongs to the opposition party",
B: "not contesting on any party’s tickets",
C: "heavily backed by the electoral commission",
D: "supported by independent party",
answer: "B. not contesting on any party’s tickets",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. Organizations which influence government policy in their favour are referred to as",
A: "political parties",
B: "civil service",
C: "pressure group",
D: "public corporation",
answer: "C. pressure group",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. The Nigerian Medical Association (NMA) was formed to",
A: "contest elections",
B: "influence government decisions",
C: "Seek political power",
D: "treat sick doctors",
answer: "B. influence government decisions",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. Public opinion can best be expressed through",
A: "a mass media",
B: "Public meeting",
C: "open confrontations",
D: "court action",
answer: "B. Public meeting (Public meetings, protests, and petitions are ways to express public opinion.)",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. Which of the following is not the characteristic of the civil service?",
A: "anonymity",
B: "impartiality",
C: "neutrality",
D: "responsibility",
answer: "D. responsibility (While civil servants have a duty to perform, they are not personally responsible for government policies.)",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. State -owned enterprises are established by",
A: "presidential orders",
B: "act of parliament",
C: "delegated legislation",
D: "bye-laws",
answer: "B. act of parliament",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. Local government are created to",
A: "select political leaders to parliament",
B: "improve government relationship",
C: "bring government closer to the people",
D: "give more powers to traditional Leaders",
answer: "C. bring government closer to the people",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. Which of the following functions is performed by local government councillors?",
A: "taking part in making of bye-laws",
B: "serving as watch dogs to the national government",
C: "collecting rate and taxes",
D: "taking care of refugees and destitutes",
answer: "A. taking part in making of bye-laws",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. Which of the following is not a reason for colonialism in Africa?",
A: "extending the Europeans political tentacles.",
B: "widening the European economic interest.",
C: "developing Africans manpower.",
D: "the search for raw materials for Europeans industries",
answer: "C. developing Africans manpower. (While colonialism brought some benefits, development of African manpower was not a primary motive.)",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. The British system of administration in the protectorates was called",
A: "indirect rule",
B: "direct rule",
C: "assimilation",
D: "association",
answer: "A. indirect rule",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. The main duty of the chiefs under the indirect rule system was to ……..",
A: "collect taxes",
B: "make laws",
C: "criticize the Europeans",
D: "oppose the educated elite",
answer: "A. collect taxes",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. The abolition of the indigent was effected by the constitution of French colonies in.",
A: "1943",
B: "1946",
C: "1950",
D: "1960",
answer: "B. 1946",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. One of the founding fathers of the National Congress of British of West Africa (NCBWA) was",
A: "Dr. Nnamdi Azikiwe",
B: "Chief Obafemi Amolowo",
C: "Sir Ahmadu Bello",
D: "Casely Hayford",
answer: "D. Casely Hayford",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. One reason for increased nationalist activities after the Second World War was the",
A: "rise in colonial support for the native chiefs",
B: "social and economic hardships",
C: "sporadic increase in the establishment of modern market",
D: "non-discrimination in the civil service",
answer: "B. social and economic hardships",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. Before the Second World War, the Executive Councils in British West Africa were exclusively reserved for the",
A: "chiefs",
B: "educated elite",
C: "village heads",
D: "white officials",
answer: "D. white officials",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. Which of the following was a characteristic of colonial constitutions?",
A: "Entrenchment of fundamental human rights",
B: "Reservation of veto power for the governor",
C: "Provision for checks and balances on the powers of the governor.",
D: "Establishment of the supreme Court for colonies",
answer: "B. Reservation of veto power for the governor",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. Military rule came into being in West Africa",
A: "before the advent of colonial rule",
B: "before the Berlin conference",
C: "after independence",
D: "during colonial rule",
answer: "C. after independence",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. Laws promulgated by military governments are called",
A: "decrees",
B: "bye-laws",
C: "acts",
D: "bills",
answer: "A. decrees",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. Which of the following countries was once a Trusteeship territory to Nigeria?",
A: "Cameroon",
B: "Burkina Faso",
C: "Niger",
D: "Chad",
answer: "A. Cameroon",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. Which of the following countries is a permanent member of the Security Council of the United Nation Organization?",
A: "Australia",
B: "Britain",
C: "India",
D: "Germany",
answer: "B. Britain",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. Which of the following was responsible for approving the budget of the Organization of African Unity (OAU)?",
A: "The Council of ministers",
B: "General secretariat",
C: "Economic and Social Commission",
D: "Commission and Mediation, Conciliation and Arbitration.",
answer: "A. The Council of ministers",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question51",
question:  "51. *******************************",
A: "*******************************",
B: "*******************************",
C: "*******************************",
D: "*******************************",
answer: "Z. zzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzz",
correctLetter: "Z",
correctOption: 9,
},

{
id: "question52",
question:  "52. The first Senegalese to be elected to the French Chamber of Deputies in 1914 was",
A: "Lamine Gueye",
B: "Camara Laye",
C: "Paul Deferre",
D: "Blaise Diagne",
answer: "D. Blaise Diagne",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question53",
question:  "53. The legislature in the United States of America Is called the",
A: "Knesset",
B: "Parliament",
C: "Congress",
D: "Diet",
answer: "C. Congress",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question54",
question:  "54. The Legislative Council of the colonial period was responsible for the passage of",
A: "decrees",
B: "edicts",
C: "acts",
D: "ordinances",
answer: "D. ordinances",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question55",
question:  "55. The political institution established to administer affairs of people at the grassroots is called a",
A: "public corporation",
B: "local authority",
C: "tribunal",
D: "regional coordinating Council",
answer: "B. local authority",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question56",
question:  "56. On which of the following grounds may a person be disqualified from voting in Ghana?",
A: "Age",
B: "Sex",
C: "Religion",
D: "Education",
answer: "C. Religion (Voting rights should not be based on religion.)",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question57",
question:  "57. A coup d’état is a",
A: "mob action by workers",
B: "sudden seizure of power by the military",
C: "demonstration by public servants",
D: "popular uprising by the citizens",
answer: "B. sudden seizure of power by the military",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question58",
question:  "58. The political sovereignly of the state is often exercised by the",
A: "executive",
B: "judiciary",
C: "parliament",
D: "electorate",
answer: "D. electorate",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question59",
question:  "59. One of the disadvantages of a representative government is that few people",
A: "form the electorate",
B: "vote for the opposition",
C: "participate actively in decision making",
D: "are educated on electoral procedure",
answer: "C. participate actively in decision making",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question60",
question:  "60. The first chairman of the National Liberation Council in Ghana was",
A: "A. Afrifa",
B: "J.A Ankrah",
C: "J. B. Danquah",
D: "K. Acheampong",
answer: "B. J.A Ankrah",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},


]